online sources: 
-----------------
http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/EclipseGit/article.html
http://www.eclipse.org/forums/index.php?t=msg&goto=648905&S=9bcfa96ab726d744d41a19c7fb02d723#msg_648905

Eclipse uses EGit plugin
--------------------------
EGit is an Eclipse plug-in (software component) which allows you to use the distributed version control system Git directly within the Eclipse IDE.
The EGit plug-in can be installed into every Eclipse IDE installation. Usually EGit supports the last two Eclipse releases.


Is EGit already installed?
---------------------------
You can check by:
1. Windows -> Preferences -> Team (if there is Git option available under Team, it means the plugin is already installed).
2. Help -> About Eclipse -> Installation Details -> Plug-ins (tab) - EGit will be listed here if installed.


To install the EGit plug-in (if not installed)
-----------------------------------------------
1. Start Eclipse installation manager via the 'Help → Install new Software' menu.
2. Plugin available from: http://download.eclipse.org/egit/updates


Configuring Git in Eclipse
----------------------------
The Eclipse Git functionality allows you to configure your default user and email address for a commit. 
1. Select "Window -> Preferences -> Team -> Git -> Configuration -> Add Entry".
2. use the user.name as key and mahabrashid as value
3. use the user.email as key and mabz@donotemail.me as value


Setup rules for ignoring files and directories (check: http://www.vogella.com/tutorials/EclipseGit/article.html to find out more)
---------------------------------------------------------------------
You can create the .gitignore file in the root directory of the working tree to make it specific for the Git repository.
You can also setup a global .gitignore file valid for all Git repositories via the core.excludesfile setting.


Working with a local Git repository in Eclipse
------------------------------------------------
1. select Team -> Share Project -> Git
2. check "Use or create in parent folder or project". Although Eclipse recommends NOT to use it (Placing Git repositories directly in the workspace may cause performance issues since the Git support in Eclipse then may need to scan a large number of files reachable under the workspace), for simplicity and to be aligned with non-eclipse versioning, it is chosen. This also helps knowing whether the project is version controlled in directory navigation (creates .git folder under the project directory) outside of Eclipse, and to package up project with its own version controlling in the same location which is especially useful in working on a removable disk.


Using the Git Staging view
---------------------------
Eclipse gives you several options to stage and commit your changes. The Git Staging view provides a convenient compact overview on all changes you have done since checking out a branch.
The Git Staging view is non-modal, you can switch between different repositories without loosing a commit message and it allows incremental staging for changes.
Open the Git Staging view via: 
Window -> Show View -> Other -> Git -> Git Staging menu.


Creating remote repository in Eclipse (remote repo will already have been created on github at this stage)
-----------------------------------------------------------------------
0.1. **Very Important** Check the name of your private key (github_rsa or id_rsa) in 'home/.ssh' directory. Check/Update in Eclipse in:
Window -> Preferences -> Network Connections -> SSH2, select 'General' tab, check the '.ssh' directory path is right, and add the private key (github_rsa, id_rsa) into the 'Private Keys' field.
1. Select Window -> Show view -> other -> Git Repositories
2. Expand the tree in Git Repositories view. Right click 'Remotes', select 'Create Remote', select 'origin'.
3. Enter the remote repo details, e.g.
URI: git@github.com:mahabrashid/RMISecurityImplicationInvestigation.git
Host: github.com
Repository Path (if connection fails, try removing the leading slash): /mahabrashid/RMISecurityImplicationInvestigation.git
Protocol: ssh (if ssh doesn't work, select https)
user: git
password: (no password needed)


Clone existing project
------------------------
Eclipse allows you to clone an existing Git repository and to import existing projects from this repository into your Eclipse workspace by using a wizard.
Select File -> Import -> Git -> Project from Git.


